All right, today's דף daf is נז, Nun-Zayin, but we start at
the very bottom of נו עמוד ב. Nun-Vav amud bet. We had
just brought in a debate from a בכור bechor making a מום
mum in an animal that had a blood clot, and explained at
least the way the גמרא Gemara phrased it was it was a
debate between the חכמים Chachamim and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, whether there's
a prohibition about making a מום mum once it already has a
מום. mum. Is the prohibition to make it to make it not
perfect, so if it already has a מום mum it's not a
problem, or is the prohibition the מום mum itself? And then the
גמרא Gemara made that as interesting parallels to other cases where the
question is how much do we focus on the act regardless of
the state that it's in, or how much is it about creating
that state? So, and specifically for us the issue was about מחמיץ
אחר מחמיץ. mechameitz achar mechameitz. That here we have said that the
prohibition is not just or maybe not, but certainly not just letting
it become חמץ, chametz, but making it into bread as חמץ chametz
or making it into the חלה, challah, the מנחה mincha as חמץ.
chametz. So even if it's already חמץ, chametz, then the other people
down the down the road of the process, the first person who
kneads it, the second person who puts it in the pans, or
the person who puts it in the oven, all of those people
transgress. It's not about letting it become חמץ, chametz, that was only
once, but it was about doing these acts as חמץ. chametz. Okay,
so now we continue with this. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
אמר רבי אמי amar Rabbi Ami four lines from the bottom נו
עמוד ב Nun-Vav amud bet two words from the end of the
line, אמר רבי אמי amar Rabbi Ami says Rabbi Ami: הניח שאור
על גבי עיסה והלך וישב לו ונתחמצה. hiniach se'or al gabei issa
vehalach veyashav lo venitchamtza. So here is exactly the question about is
the prohibition only doing אפייה, afiya, לישה, lisha, עריכה, aricha, doing the
stage of making bread when it's חמץ, chametz, or is there also
that aspect of the prohibition of making it חמץ? chametz? Now, it's
interesting that he did not talk about just being lazy and letting
it become חמץ, chametz, because maybe then you could say well, what's
to say you let it rather than everybody else in the room
let it? You know, what's to sort of pin that on you?
Besides that it's אין בו מעשה ein bo maaseh so you wouldn't
get מלקות. malkus. And if you say well, maybe I was the
one kneading it and I was negligent and it became חמץ? chametz?
Well then that would be the category of kneading it as חמץ.
chametz. So this is the more interesting question which is you weren't
kneading it, you weren't just standing around doing nothing, you actually put
sourdough into this into this dough and walked away and let it
become חמץ. chametz. So you were מחמיץ mechameitz the dough, but you
did not do one of the stages of making it, making it
into the חלה. challah. Okay, so what is your story? ונתחמצה, venitchamtza,
wait a minute, so it became חמץ chametz מאליה me'eleiha on its
own, חייב עליה כמעשה שבת, chayav aleiha k'maaseh Shabbos, and he's חייב
chayav just like by שבת. Shabbos. Now, we'll see by שבת Shabbos
in a minute, but it means that what's שבת? Shabbos? Isn't that
exactly what baking is in שבת? Shabbos? You put it in the
oven, you walk away, it finishes baking, you're חייב. chayav. Okay, so
here too, you put on the חמץ, chametz, you walk away, it
becomes חמץ, chametz, you're חייב chayav even though you didn't actively involve
yourself with it while it was becoming חמץ. chametz. Of course, the
question is how do you define what the prohibition is? Every category
needs to be defined what the prohibition is. By שבת Shabbos the
prohibition is cooking, so we define cooking by putting it in the
oven, even though the rest happens later. Here, if the prohibition is
doing a stage of the process while it's חמץ, chametz, you didn't
do a stage of the process while it's חמץ. chametz. So it's
not the comparison isn't exactly the same because you have to ask
yourself, is there a prohibition here of just making it חמץ? chametz?
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, a little תוספות
Tosafot addressed this. תוספות Tosafot says: הניח שאור על גבי עיסה והלך
וישב לו ונתחמצה מאליה, hiniach se'or al gabei issa vehalach veyashav lo
venitchamtza me'eleiha, דאף על גב דכתיב לא תעשה ולא תאפה, de'af al
gav dechtiv lo teaseh velo te'afeh, don't do it and don't bake
it, משמע דידי עשייה, mashma di'yedei asiya, מידי עשייה, midei asiya, something
of actually a stage of making it into bread, כגון לישה ועריכה
ואפייה וקטיפה, kegon lisha ve'aricha ve'afiya ve'ktifa, all the things we mentioned.
It doesn't just say don't make it חמץ, chametz, it says don't
bake it, in the way we understand don't do these processes of
making חמץ, chametz, the slapping of the dough. Okay, הכא נמי לא
תעשה קרינן ביה. hacha nami lo teaseh karinan bei.
Now I think what תוספות Tosafot really means to say is לא
תעשה קרינן ביה, lo teaseh karinan bei, because לא תעשה חמץ lo
ta'aseh chametz means don't make, תעשה te'aseh means don't allow it to
become חמץ. chametz. It shall not be made חמץ, chametz, right? Which
basically means you're a little more passive and you're allowing it to
become חמץ chametz as opposed to לא תעשה חמץ lo ta'aseh chametz
could be understood the way the גמרא Gemara was understanding, which is:
don't make it into the מנחה mincha as חמץ. chametz. Okay, so
anyway תוספות Tosafot is saying that really if you think about it,
פשט pshat of לא תעשה חמץ lo teaseh chametz is more just
allowing it to become חמץ. chametz. But that is conceptually what the
גמרא Gemara is introducing. The prohibition is not just doing a stage
of the process, which allowed us to say that later people down
the road are also חייב. chayav. The prohibition is also making it
חמץ chametz without doing an act of the process of making it
a מנחה. mincha. So that allows you, if you would, the worst
of both worlds. If you just make it חמץ chametz you're חייב,
chayav, but even if it's already חמץ, chametz, if you keep on
doing the process of making it into the מנחה, mincha, you're חייב
chayav as well. Yes?
If you've done absolutely nothing though yet that as a מנחה, mincha,
like then why isn't this just סתם stam flour?
Right, so we are going to see later that... The assumption with
all of this is that it already has קדושת כלי kedushas kli
and it already is defined as a מנחה. mincha. You're absolutely correct
and that's going to be necessary. So that is correct.
Even though at these points you don't necessarily need the כהן Kohen
gets involved
but this could be done ידי בעלים, yidei be'alim, absolutely correct. So
it's possible that people that are being transgressing here are not כהנים.
Kohanim. Okay, yes?
The way that as soon as it's put in the vessel that
already becomes קודש kodesh without anything else, so one pours it into
a vessel.
Yeah. So yeah, the vessel makes it, gives it the קדושת מנחה.
kedushas mincha.
I see, so that's already that person who put that initially put
it in the vessel is positive?
Yeah. Okay, but now that it has קדושת מנחה, kedushas mincha, don't
start making it חמץ. chametz. I see. Okay, if you did it
before you put it in the כלי, kli, we'll discuss this actually
later today, then you haven't transgressed, what happened before you haven't transgressed.
Okay, so let's take a look. Now the question is what's the
comparison to שבת Shabbos other than the fact that שבת Shabbos by
baking let's say has a passive part. ומעשה שבת כהאי גוונא מי
מיחייב, U'ma'aseh Shabbos ke'hai gavna mi michayev, why are you חייב chayav
by שבת Shabbos in such a case? אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, doesn't
רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana say in the name
of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: הניח בשר על גבי גחלים, Hiniach basar
al gabi gechalim, if a person put some meat on coals on
שבת, Shabbos, הפכו חייב לא הפכו פטור. Hiphcho chayav lo hiphcho patur.
If you flipped it over you're חייב, chayav, if you didn't flip
it over you're פטור. patur. We'll see in a minute because it
won't cook enough if you just leave it on, you know, coals
and therefore it won't really cook and won't be considered that you've
done the שיעור shiur of cooking, as we'll see in a minute.
But anyway, but if you flipped it over and it got cooked
on both sides, you're חייב. chayav. Anyway, we'll see about that in
a minute in the גמרא, Gemara, that's going to be about the
שיעור. shiur. The question here is: Ah, so just putting it on
isn't enough if you're not it's not doing a good job. And
the way תוספות Tosafos explains it here that we're assuming here as
well it's not a good job because the way it explained it
was he just put the sourdough on and you walked away. Now
if anybody's making bread, you know what you don't do is you
don't just put a sourdough on and walk away. You knead the
sourdough into it, you get it to diffuse throughout the whole thing.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying that's not be enough of חמץ,
chametz, that's like an imperfect making of it of חמץ, chametz, like
an imperfect cooking and therefore you should be פטור patur unless it
יתחמצן. yis-chamtsan. Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
אמר רבא מאי חייב נמי דקאמר למעשה צלי של שבת. Amar Rava
mai chayav nami de'ka'amar le'ma'aseh tzli shel Shabbos. No, רבא Rava says,
look, it means when you're חייב chayav it means you're חייב chayav
as if you had done a good cooking on שבת, Shabbos, a
roasting, meaning here was because you put it on coals, but you
didn't put it on coals on שבת, Shabbos, let's say you put
it on a nice strong flame on your barbecue and you threw
it on the barbecue, then you're חייב chayav without flipping it over.
So, you know, so the comparison is not putting it on the
coals, it's comparing as to putting it on the barbecue.
So here too, after a time, right, right.
But as Michael says, you know, presumably what we're saying here is
that even if you put the sourdough and walk away, it will
make it enough חמץ. chametz. Okay, so you have to figure out
what's your point of comparison. So don't worry and bother me about
the coals, fine, the point is it makes it חמץ. chametz. So
then what is the point of the comparison? So the point of
comparison seems to be what Mordechai said which I said earlier, not
to say how well it became חמץ chametz but to say there
could be a passive component. You don't have to be actively doing
it the whole time, you can do one stage and it happens
later. Again, it's still a חידוש chiddush here because here we are
saying both things. We're saying number one even if it's already חמץ
chametz you're חייב chayav because it's about doing every stage while it's
חמץ, chametz, and now we're saying there's also prohibition not about doing
a stage of the process but just making it חמץ. chametz. So
you have both ends.
But if I'm the whoever it is and I let, you know,
and I notice some sourdough fell in there and I don't do
anything about
it, then you've not, no, correct. Presumably you are not only just
not, you know, לאו שיש בו מעשה, lav sheyesh bo ma'aseh, presumably
you haven't even done the איסור. issur. The איסור issur is actually
actively
making
it חמץ, chametz, correct.
But you used the opportunity to save the zman from being baked.
Exactly! Exactly! חשיבותא chashivusa of the bomb way.
Sorry everybody,
all the my technical fidgeting. Correct. Okay, let's keep on going. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: now we're going to have
a little digression about שבת Shabbos and how much do you have
to cook to be חייב chayav on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, גופא, Gufa,
let's look at this case that we just brought in indirectly. אמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן הניח בשר על גבי גחלים,
Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan hiniach basar al gabi
gechalim, if you left your, if you put, I shouldn't say left,
you placed meat on coals on שבת, Shabbos, הפכו חייב לא הפכו
פטור. Hiphcho chayav lo hiphcho patur. If you slipped it over you're
חייב, chayav, if you didn't you're פטור. patur. So the גמרא Gemara
says, hey, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא דלא הפכו
לא בשיל, Ilima d'lo hiphcho lo bashil,
if that it would not cook if you didn't flip it over
because it's only on coals, it's not on a fire, so nothing
was going to get cooked, right? So therefore you're only חייב chayav
if you flipped it over. פשיטא, Pshita, of course, who needs רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to tell me that? Of course you need to
do something more to be חייב. chayav. You'll look at it and
you'll see it's not cooked. אלא, Ella, so maybe the case is
דאי לא מהפך ליה נמי הוה בשיל. de'i lo mehaphach leh nami
hava bashil. Maybe the case is even without you flipping it over
it would get cooked. So אמאי לא מיחייב, amai lo michayev, why
wouldn't you be חייב? chayav? Why would you need to flip it
over? Don't flip it over, let it continue to get cooked by
itself. So the גמרא Gemara says now I will tell you that
there is an obvious answer that could have said here which is
a bit מחלוקת machlokes in the אחרונים acharonim by הלכות שבת. hilchos
Shabbos. Very often when the גמרא Gemara asks these questions, the way
it answers them, there's like almost a trope that it has sometimes
about cooking when it speaks about if you stirred it, if you
did this, and the גמרא Gemara says, well why did you
need to do? If it would have happened by itself, then it's
obvious. And often the answer is no, no, no, it would have
happened by itself, but you made it happen quicker. Okay, so why
didn't the גמרא Gemara say that? Well you could take—if it would
have happened anyway, you're חייב chayav on שבת Shabbos whether you made
it happen quicker or didn't make it happen quicker, if it would
have cooked anyway. But not necessarily. There's a very interesting debate of
the אחרונים achronim that says: what happens if I put my food
in the oven on שבת, Shabbos, but it only finishes cooking after
שבת? Shabbos? Okay, everybody agrees that if it doesn't finish cooking—somebody took
it off the oven before it finished cooking—I'm פטור. patur. It has
to finish cooking. But the question is, does it have to finish
cooking on שבת? Shabbos? Or is it like because I finish the
מלאכה melacha when it finishes cooking, or once it finished cooking, I'm
חייב chayav for putting it in the oven?
Okay, so you think cooking on שבת Shabbos is the problem. I'm
allowed to cook after שבת. Shabbos.
So you think it has to finish on שבת. Shabbos.
Yeah, that's what I would think.
Oh, and so, but a טשולנט? cholent?
So if I go ahead and I put my chicken in the
oven, and it's whatever it is, 6:00 PM Saturday night, and שבת
Shabbos is over at 6:30, and by the time it's 6:30, right,
the chicken is still inedible, everybody here thinks that I haven't transgressed,
even though it finishes cooking after שבת Shabbos and I put it
in the oven. Yes, right? Oh my god. Okay, alright. Well, it's
nice to know that you've all made that decision, you should know
it's a debate of the אחרונים, achronim, but here's the issue. No,
I don't know you're wrong, it's a debate of the אחרונים, achronim,
it's an unresolved question. But, thank you, but, hush, hush,
quiet,
okay, okay. So, if that were true, the גמרא Gemara had a
very easy answer, could have said here it just did it. It
could have said that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying, that
you put it on the coals, it does not, it'll finish cook
by itself, but it'll only finish after שבת. Shabbos. And you're not
חייב chayav unless you flip it over and you speed it up
and you get it to finish on שבת. Shabbos. So I just
want to point out that it's interesting the גמרא Gemara didn't go
there, because the גמרא Gemara usually in these scenarios says the case
is, is that yes it would have happened anyway, but you're חייב
chayav because you speeded it up. And it could have said that
here if what everybody is saying is right.
So what's the rationale for not to say you're not חייב? chayav?
I mean, you are חייב? chayav?
You are חייב chayav because they say the מלאכה melacha is defined
as putting it on the fire, provided that eventually it cooks.
Even if it's like two weeks later?
Or yeah, although usually it won't be two weeks, but you know
what I mean. Okay, anyway, let's move on. So this is the
גמרא's Gemara question. So the גמרא's Gemara question is, why did you
have to flip it if it was going to happen anyway? And
the גמרא Gemara does not say that you speeded it up because
it would presumably say speeded it up or not speeded it up,
it was going to happen anyway, you'd be חייב. chayav. But let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So the
גמרא Gemara says, look, צריכא, tzricha, you need it for the following
case: אי לא הפיך בה הוי בשול מצד אחד כמאכל בן דרוסאי.
ee lo hiphech bah, havei bashul mitzad echad k'maachal Ben Drusai. If
you would have not flipped it over, yes it would have cooked
a little bit, but how much would it have cooked? It would
have cooked on one side כמאכל בן דרוסאי. k'maachal Ben Drusai. מאכל
בן דרוסאי Maachal Ben Drusai is—whoever בן דרוסאי Ben Drusai was, whether
he was a person or whether it was a symbol, but whatever
it meant, basically the way bandits eat, which is basically like half
raw. Okay, now there's a debate actually of רש"י Rashi and the
רמב"ם. Rambam. רש"י Rashi says it means a third cooked, the רמב"ם
Rambam says it means half cooked. Again, it's not even clear what
they mean when they say a third and a half. What does
that mean? Does that mean that if let's say the chicken takes
two hours to cook, a third cooked is after having been in
the oven for whatever, let's be easy, three hours. The chicken takes
three hours to cook. Okay, so is a third cooked it's been
in an hour and half cooked it's been an hour and a
half? Or no,
sometimes if you've cooked it, it's been in the oven for an
hour, it hasn't really begun cooking yet at all. I mean, I
don't know, but you know, it's not like how you measure what
a third and a half cooked means is also a question. But
whatever it is, it's a type of cooking where the גמרא Gemara
says it could be eaten בשעת הדחק, b'shaas hadchak, if you really
were forcing me I'd eat it, but most people don't consider it
ready yet. Okay, but that is enough to be חייב chayav on
שבת Shabbos once you get something to מאכל בן דרוסאי. maachal Ben
Drusai. So here the question is, what if the whole piece isn't
at מאכל בן דרוסאי? maachal Ben Drusai? What would be if, you
know, you got your nice steak and the top part is still
raw, it hasn't even cooked at all, the bottom part is—is like
rare? Okay, you know, most people, you know, won't eat rare. I
mean, there's some people that love it, but most people—some love rare.
Okay, most people's—also it depends, Jews' idea of rare is a lot
more cooked than I think non-Jews' idea of rare. You know, but
anyway, okay fine. Alright, anyway, so let's say the bottom part is
rare and the top part is raw. Okay, so he says you're
not חייב. chayav. Why not? Why? Because although it's מאכל בן דרוסאי,
maachal Ben Drusai, and although—this is the bizarre idea—it works
for שבת Shabbos
but not—and although it's the right amount, כגרוגרת, k'grogeres, or whatever quantity
it requires, but nobody would eat this piece of meat. Nobody would
eat a piece of meat where the bottom part is rare which
most people only eat בשעת הדחק b'shaas hadchak and the top part
is raw. Now the irony is, if it were a thinner piece
of meat, right, and you just had a thin piece of meat
which was rare, you'd be חייב. chayav. But because it it exists
as part of a thick piece of meat and the top part
of it is raw, nobody—it's not the normal way to cook it,
it's not considered like you did an act of cooking because nobody
is prepared to eat that piece of meat.
So you're never חייב chayav on שווארמה shawarma because only cooking the
outer surface? There's a tiny little minority
cooked...
No, because
that's...
because the outer part is not מאכל בן דרוסאי, ma'achal ben drosai,
the outer part is כולו, kulo, which we're going to get to
in a minute. Okay, so let's keep on going. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so therefore if you would have left it on the flame
you're not חייב. chayav. וכי מהפך בה ve-ki mahapach bei and when
you flip over the piece of meat בשול משתי צדדים למאכל בן
דרוסאי. bashul mishtei staddim le-ma'achal ben drosai. Then both sides get to
be מאכל בן דרוסאי, ma'achal ben drosai, both sides get to be
rare. So there when we're going to say מאכל בן דרוסאי ma'achal
ben drosai is enough because you could eat it בשעת הדחק besha'at
hadechak if you needed to, that's when the whole piece is מאכל
בן דרוסאי, ma'achal ben drosai, not when it's half מאכל בן דרוסאי
ma'achal ben drosai and half raw. Raw, excuse me. So both sides
are מאכל בן דרוסאי ma'achal ben drosai then we could say you're
חייב chayav for שבת Shabbat but any less than that, even if
were the piece thinner you would have been מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat,
the way it is right now it's not considered in any way
fit to be eaten and therefore it's not considered to be an
act of cooking. Okay?
So even if you leave it on and then it ultimately will
be?
No, if ultimately it is cooking on שבת Shabbat let's assume if
it is on שבת Shabbat yes it's cooked. Well, let's I'm not
going to get... let's assume whatever the time period is that you
are prepared that you would look at the end of the process,
if eventually it will then obviously you're חייב. chayav. Okay but the
point here is is that no this is as far as it's
going to cook period, either as far as it'll cook on שבת
Shabbat if only שבת Shabbat is relevant or as far as it
will cook period. And therefore you're not חייב chayav unless you flip
it. Let me just read
the rest of the line where it spells it out. וקמשמע לן
ve-kamashma lan and it is teaching you דכי מטי צד אחד כמאכל
בן דרוסאי לאו כלום הוא de-ki mati tzad echad kema'achal ben drosai
lav klum hu that if it's only on one side מאכל בן
דרוסאי ma'achal ben drosai it's not enough. If you're doing only מאכל
בן דרוסאי ma'achal ben drosai to be considered edible it has to
be two sides. I'll take your question in a minute but I
want to see the contrast with it which will even further clarify
it which is sort of you know Mordechai's point about shawarma. The
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא, amar Rava, רבא Rava says
ואם נצלה בו כגרוגרת מצד אחד במקום אחד חייב. ve-im nitzla bo
kegrogeret mitzad echad bemakom echad chayav.
If however it's not מאכל בן דרוסאי ma'achal ben drosai but נצלה
nitzla roasted which means that it's fully cooked but it didn't go
all the way through. So I put my steak on the barbecue
on the grill and it was you know a very high flame
so what happened was was that the outer shell got cooked and
the rest remains raw. Okay? Or Mordechai says that's what happens with
a shawarma. So in that type of a case although half of
the piece is raw since the bottom half of the piece is
fully cooked and normal people eat fully cooked, that's something that I
am prepared to eat. So really the question is what does it
mean that this are you prepared to eat this piece? If it's
half raw and half rare no person is prepared to eat it.
Okay? If however it's rare on both sides or it's fully cooked
on one side and raw on the other that's a type of
piece of meat that somebody will eat. Yes, Mordechai.
And I'm wondering though if focusing on the time is of like
a red herring when we're also the presented is the coal, right?
That you're putting this onto the coals that they themselves don't have
the potential to cook anymore beyond this point. So at the outset
when I put it on it couldn't have finished cooking in this
case. Here though the question of שבת Shabbat is that time-lapse.
So you're saying the reason the גמרא Gemara you're going back to
my earlier point that maybe the reason the גמרא Gemara did not
tell you that you're speeding it up is because maybe you know
it's not שייך shayach to be... it's not like it would have
happened anyway. Right, that could be. All right, so anyway yes.
What's wrong with that טשולנט cholent from a minute ago?
Let's talk about טשולנט. cholent.
Yes. So at the time before שבת Shabbat it has to be
cooked or anything that starts before שבת Shabbat is and it's a
מלאכה. melacha. We're asking the flip case where it started on שבת
Shabbat and ended after but go ahead.
But it has
to be edible before
שבת. Shabbat. But but the longer it cooks overnight the better it
gets. Right. It does so you are cooking it yet you say
don't touch it
so there is no prohibition to let things cook on שבת. Shabbat.
The prohibition is to cook which requires you to do an act.
Okay so you to do an act means you can't put something
on the fire on שבת. Shabbat. So when you put it on
before שבת Shabbat and it cooks on שבת Shabbat you're right that's
correct. The case I was asking was the exact mirror image of
that where you put it on שבת Shabbat and you let it
cook after.
Okay so the
mirror image of the טשולנט. cholent. And the question is you certainly
need to do the act of putting it on the fire. The
question is and that's why you can let your טשולנט cholent cook
on שבת. Shabbat. The question is is that sufficient or do you
say no no no not only do you need the act of
putting it on the fire you need to actually finish cooking on
שבת Shabbat as well. That's the question that the אחרונים achronim ask.
Anyway the גמרא Gemara is not addressing it I was just bringing
it in. What the גמרא Gemara is saying is how cooked is
cooked to be considered like you've done a מלאכה? melacha? Part of
it has to be is it fit for eating. So if it's
a thick piece even if it had been a thin piece it
would have been fit to be eaten because you have enough that
was מאכל בן דרוסאי. ma'achal ben drosai. As it exists now nobody
eats a piece of meat that's half raw and half rare. However
if the outside is fully cooked or if it's rare on both
sides then it is fit to be eaten and then it is
a מלאכה melacha of cooking. Okay? So now we'll continue. Bobby do
you have a question or ready to go on? No? Okay. So
let's...
I'm hungry for...
All right exactly. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina le-Rav
Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי. Rav Ashi. No,
so it's a דיוק diyuk on Rava's statement. Rava just said בצד
אחד betzad echad and, I'm sorry, אמר רבא Amar Rava ניצבו initzbu
כגרוגרת kegogeres מצד אחד mitzad echad במקום אחד bemakom echad חייב. chayav.
Right, Rava did not just say one צד tzad was fully cooked,
he also said the גרוגרת, gogeres, that's the amount you have to
cook to be חייב, chayav, which is the size of what is
it, a pressed, I'll get it wrong, date or fig, whatever it
is, a pressed stuff. Anyway, a certain, what, fig? Okay, thank you.
It's a certain size. So anyway, if he says if it's all
on one side, fully cooked, and it's all in one place, which
doesn't, which means you don't have a patch that's cooked here and
a patch that's cooked there, right? It's all local, it's all together
that one place that's fully cooked. Because then presumably I could just
take from that one place and eat it. Okay, that's when you're
חייב. chayav. So the question is, do you really need במקום אחד?
bemakom echad? So let's take a look. אמר
ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so Ravina said
to Rav Ashi, במקום אחד אין בשתים או גמל מקומות bemakom echad
in b'shtaim o gimel mekomot לא? lo? Are you telling me only
one place and not two or three places, it would not be
good that you cannot combine
it? והתנן, Vehasnan, we learned in a משנה Mishnah by a totally
different מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbos, הקודח כל שהוא חייב, hakodeach kol
shehu chayav, that if you make the tiniest little hole in like
a box or a wall, you're חייב chayav because of בונה. boneh.
Okay, so you take your awl, A-W-L, and you make a hole
in the wall, or you make a hole in a box, you're
חייב, chayav, you've constructed something. So the גמרא Gemara assumes what is
one hole going to be used to construct with? You can't really
be חייב chayav just for one hole. So let's take a look.
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא Ilima במקום אחד, bemakom
echad, that you made the hole in one place, כל שהוא למאי
חזי, kol shehu l'mai chazi, what can you use one lousy hole
for? אלא לאו, Ela lav, when it says if you make one
hole you're חייב chayav on שבת, Shabbos, בשנים ושלש מקומות, bishnayim ushlosh
mekomos, it must mean that you made one hole in two or
three different places. Okay, so although it's a hard read, it's כל
שהוא, kol shehu, but it's understanding that the כל שהוא kol shehu
does not refer to the size of the hole. So each hole
is a tiny hole, but if you make a couple of them,
then you're חייב. chayav. Why? Because דחזי לצירוף, dechazi l'tziruf, because it
somehow can be combined. Now, how do you combine two or three
holes? You know, Rashi doesn't say, what, you make two or three
holes in the near proximity, but they're distinct holes, then eventually you
somehow that you know combined can combine them into one hole. Doesn't
really answer the question, because if they're not yet combined into one
hole, if they still remain as distinct holes, then what, and you
think you need a big hole to have done something significant, how
could they? In a way, it's much harder than eating, you know,
cooking.
You know, cooking you could say in theory I can eat a
little piece here, a little piece here, a little piece here, and
eat enough to be חייב, chayav, you know, so that you'll have
said you've cooked enough pieces that fit to be eaten, even though
I have to cut them from different places of the piece of
meat. But here, you know, if I can't use it the way
it is with the little holes in the wall, then it's still
not usable. But maybe that's the point, so קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
if there a lot of little holes, you know, can combine, even
if they're not yet fully combined yet, but because you can maybe,
you know, finish the job and combine them, so here too cooking
a piece of meat, if you, you know, who needs it all
to be in one place? If it's a little bit cooked there,
and a little there, and a little there, and I could cut
out the pieces and eat it, shouldn't that be enough to combine?
So in בונה boneh a window?
Well, that's the question anyway. So let's see what the answer is
and that'll help us understand. So the גמרא Gemara says, so לא
לעולם במקום אחד, lo l'olam bemakom echad,
really you made your tiny little hole in one place. What good
is it for? דחזי לבבא דאקלידא. dechazi l'vava d'aklida. You know what
it's good for? It's good for the, what do you call it,
you know, the thing of the, what? Not a peephole. What do
you, when you have a lock, when you have, what's the bar
that goes through? You know, deadbolt. Right. So it's good for the
bolt of a lock. Okay. Yes, it's a tiny little hole, but
even a small hole can do something. You can affix, like, we're
assuming here that where the question is where's the hole. So if
the hole's let's say on a box and you make a little
hole in one place, you can attach on the other side a
lock mechanism and have the bolt go into there. So yes, one
hole is sufficient. Now, it's even easier if it's a hole in
the wall, and the גמרא Gemara says it's elsewhere, of course you
can do something with a hole in the wall. You can put
in a nail and hang a picture on it. Okay. So, you
know, even one hole is meaningful. The question is do you need
the nail there, you know, to have done בונה. boneh. Is the
hole enough to do בונה boneh because you could put a nail
there.
But anyway, that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer. You cannot prove anything here
of two or three places because who said you're trying to make
a bigger hole? Maybe we are just talking about one hole. Okay.
So now let's continue.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some
say the same issue except it started in the other place. ואיכא
דאמרי, Ve'ika d'amri, אמר רבא, amar Rava, אפילו בשנים וג מקומות, afilu
bishnayim vegimel mekomos, even in two or three places, even if this
piece of meat is only cooked in two or three different places
and you have to combine the places, if there's enough quantity that's
cooked, you're חייב. chayav. So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei
Ravina l'Rav Ashi, אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami tanina. We
taught similarly in a משנה mishna that if you do little pieces
in different places you can conceptually combine it, הקודח ha-kodeach כל שהוא
kol she-hu חייב, chayav, if you make even the smallest hole you're
חייב, chayav, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילמא במקום אחד
ileima be-makom echad if it's in one place, כל שהוא למאי חזי
kol she-hu le-mai chazi what can one little hole help you for,
so that can't be building, אלא בשנים ובשלושה מקומות ela bi-shenayim u-vi-shelosha
mekomot it must be two or three sort of places nearby that
you're חייב chayav why דחזי לצירוף de-chazi le-tzeruf because in theory you
can now combine those holes and do something significant. And there, and
like I said it's a קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, there you actually
would have to do another act of construction but nevertheless if they
could in theory be combined that's why you're חייב, chayav, so certainly
if your piece of meat is cooked only in two or three
disparate places it should be enough to be חייב chayav because in
theory you could cut out those pieces and combine them. Okay, so
that's what he says. So the גמרא Gemara says that doesn't prove
it. לא לעולם במקום אחד lo le-olam be-makom echad the case of
the hole is not necessarily talking about multiple holes, it's talking about
one, and what good is it for? דחזי לאבבא דאקלידא de-chazi le-avava
de-aklida it is good for the bolt of a lock and it
doesn't prove anything about combining. So we had a very fascinating little
digression here about cooking on שבת, Shabbat, and the upshot of it
is that
yes it's defined as cooking
even if you just make it rare, מאכל בן דרוסאי, ma'achal ben
Drusai, but the גמרא Gemara says you don't just look at oh
is there enough rare meat here that a person could cut out
that meat and eat it. No, since it exists within a whole
piece of meat and the other half of it is raw, we
would say nobody would eat this meat the way it is even
if in theory they could cut out the bottom and eat the
bottom, and therefore you are not חייב. chayav. When are you חייב?
chayav? If it's rare on both sides, there are people that will
eat a piece of meat that's fully rare on both sides, or
if it is fully cooked on one side, then we say even
though nobody wants the raw part they will eat the fully cooked
part, and there the question is does the quantity have to be
a גרוגרת grogeret the size of a pressed fig, you need to
cook that amount to be חייב, chayav, does that quantity have to
be in one מקום makom or can it be spread out? Again
in theory somebody could cut different pieces and eat a significant amount,
but people don't eat in theory, people eat in practice, and if
nobody is going to eat this piece of meat the way it
is, can we actually say that you have cooked it? Okay, and
that is a question that has not been resolved. Now we get
to turn back to our case, away from שבת Shabbat back to
making מנחות. minchos. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, we
taught in a ברייתא, braita,
אילו נאמר אשר תקריבו לה' לא תעשה חמץ ilu ne'emar asher takrivu
l'Hashem lo teaseh chametz things that you will bring to God you
shall not make
חמץ, chametz, הייתי אומר hayiti omer אין לי בלא תעשה ein li
be-lo ta'aseh חמץ אלא קומץ, chametz ela kometz, I only the only
prohibition would apply to the actual קומץ, kometz, the handbreadth, because that
is the only thing that you're מקריב לה', makriv l'Hashem, that's the
only thing that you put on the מזבח. mizbeach. And therefore I
might have said אלא קומץ בלבד, ela kometz bilvad, מנחה מניין mincha
minayin how do I know I transgress on the whole מנחה? mincha?
Now there are three stages there are two stages and three things
to think about. One is I haven't taken the קומץ kometz yet.
I have the whole מנחה mincha without the קומץ kometz designated. That's
what the גמרא Gemara is talking about here, the מנחה. mincha. The
next stage is I took the קומץ kometz and now I have
two parts, the קומץ kometz and the שיריים. shirayim. Okay, the קומץ
kometz goes on the מזבח mizbeach the שיריים shirayim is eaten by
the כהנים. kohanim. We've already learned in the beginning of the גמרא
Gemara that the שיריים shirayim you're חייב chayav for if you make
חמץ chametz because of a דרשא drasha לא תעשה חמץ חלקם. lo
teaseh chametz chelkom. Here the question is not starting as of שיריים,
shirayim, the question is how do I know you're חייב chayav if
you let the whole מנחה mincha become חמץ? chametz? Maybe only חייב
chayav once the קומץ kometz has been designated and you let the
קומץ kometz become חמץ chametz because Torah says that that you will
give to God don't make חמץ. chametz. So that only is the
specific קומץ kometz once it's been designated. How do I know it
applies to the whole מנחה? mincha? תלמוד לומר מנחה, talmud lomar mincha,
it says it doesn't say אשר תקריבו לה' לא תעשה חמץ asher
takrivu l'Hashem lo teaseh chametz what you give to God it says
כל מנחה אשר תקריבו לה' לא תעשה חמץ, kol mincha asher takrivu
l'Hashem lo teaseh chametz, every מנחה mincha that you give to God
don't make חמץ, chametz, so it applies even to the מנחה mincha
as a whole and not just once the קומץ kometz has been
taken and just the קומץ kometz part of it. Okay, so it
says כל מנחה. kol mincha. So now it goes on, תלמוד לומר
מנחה. talmud lomar mincha. שאר מנחות מניין shear minchos minayin this is
only said by one of the מנחות. minchos. How do I know
that it applies to all the other מנחות, minchos, right this is
only said by I forget which one, but by only one of
them, רש"י Rashi says where is it, oh
yeah this is just by the מרחשת. marcheshes. So how do I
know by all the other מנחות minchos that are not the מרחשת,
marcheshes, maybe it's only prohibition by the מרחשת? marcheshes? תלמוד לומר כל
מנחה, talmud lomar kol mincha, every מנחה mincha אשר תקריבו לה'. asher
takrivu l'Hashem. Okay now, so therefore what do I learn from the
way the פסוק pasuk is phrased? Because it says מנחה mincha I
learn that it's not only the קומץ, kometz, it applies to the
whole מנחה. mincha. Because it says כל מנחה kol mincha I learn
it's not only to the מנחה mincha of מרחשת, marcheshes, it applies
to every מנחה. mincha. So what's left is to ask the question
is what do I do with אשר תקריבו לה'? asher takrivu l'Hashem?
Why did you need that if it applies to the whole מנחה?
mincha? So let's take a look. So it says like this, אשר
תקריבו לה', asher takrivu l'Hashem, so what's אשר תקריבו לה' asher takrivu
l'Hashem saying? כשרה ולא פסולה, kshera velo psula, only if it's fit
to be brought as a קרבן. korban. If the מנחה mincha becomes
פסולה psula and then I make it חמץ, chametz, then I have
not transgressed, which makes sense, right the problem of making it חמץ.
chametz. Is because it's חמץ chametz, *chametz* can't go on the מזבח
mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*, and therefore you can't make it חמץ chametz *chametz* if
it's in line for going on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach*. Okay, but
if it's already not going on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*, it's already
פסול pasul *pasul*, then there's no problem of making it חמץ chametz
*chametz*. Okay. מכאן אמרו
*mikan amru*, from here they said, המחמיץ את הכשרה חייב chayav *hamachmitz
et hakesheira chayav*, if you make a kosher מנחה mincha, *mincha* חמץ
chametz. *chametz*, then you've transgressed. ואת הפסולה פטור patur *v'et hapsula patur*.
However, if the מנחה mincha *mincha* is already פסול pasul *pasul* and
you made it חמץ chametz *chametz*, you are exempt. Now there's one
exception to this rule. You know what the exception is? What we
learned yesterday. That what's if you've already allowed it to become חמץ
chametz *chametz* and you continue to make it as חמץ chametz. *chametz*,
you're חייב chayav. *chayav* for every later stage, even though it's already
פסול pasul *pasul*, right? Because it's already חמץ chametz *chametz*, it already
can't be brought, and you're continuing to make it. Okay, but that's
in a way what the תורה Torah *Torah* says within the context
context
bracketing the fact that it's already חמץ chametz. *chametz* and פסול pasul.
*pasul*, don't be making it חמץ chametz. *chametz*. But if it's פסול
pasul *pasul* for some other reason, then it's no longer relevant. It's
like our good friend פיגול *pigul*. What פיגול *pigul* is, you know,
if you know, it's sort of like if bracketing פיגול *pigul* it
would have been כשר *kasher*, I'm חייב chayav *chayav* for פיגול *pigul*.
If it would have been פסול pasul *pasul* because of some non-פיגול
*pigul* reason, I'm not חייב chayav *chayav* for פיגול *pigul*. So here
too, if it would have been פסול *pasul* for some non-חמץ chametz
*chametz* reason, I'm not חייב chayav *chayav* for making it חמץ chametz,
*chametz*. I'm only חייב chayav *chayav* for making something that could be
going on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*. But if it's פסול *pasul* because
it's חמץ chametz *chametz* and I continue to make it, then I
continue to be חייב chayav *chayav*. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to ask an interesting variation of that. So let's
take a look. בעי רב פפא Rav Pappa *Ba'ei Rav Pappa*, so
רב פפא *Rav Pappa* asks the question, חמצה ויצא וחזרה וחמצה מהו
*chamtza v'yatza v'chazara v'chamtza mahu*? It became חמץ chametz. *chametz*, or you
made it חמץ chametz. *chametz*, then you took it out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, so now it's פסול *pasul* because
it's
יוצא yotzei *yotzei*, right? That's the way it can become פסול *pasul*.
The basic way something can become פסול *pasul* is either it goes
out of the מקדש mikadesh *Mikdash* or it becomes טמא *tamei*. Okay,
so those are the two ways. חמץ chametz, *chametz* is a special
new thing. Anyway, you made it חמץ chametz *chametz*, you took it
out of the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash *Beis HaMikdash*, you brought it
back in, and now you finished doing the עבודה *avoda*. So here
I was, I kneaded the dough, and I was being negligent or
I threw in sourdough, I made it חמץ chametz. *chametz*. I transgressed.
Now I said, oh my god, פסול *pasul*, take it out, get
rid of it. We took it out of the מקדש Mekadesh *Mikdash*.
Then somebody wasn't thinking or he said what the heck, he brought
it back in the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* and I now went and
baked it. Okay, have I now been חייב chayav *chayav*? Thinking whether
I thought what I knew what I did, that's a separate question.
But the question first is not liability, but has it been the
transgression? We've discussed later whether I'm liable or not. Okay, but whatever
it was, I went and I baked it. So have I now
חייב chayav *chayav* because I baked this you know whatever חמץ chametz.
*chametz*? Or do we say no, it was already פסול *pasul*, it
was already יוצא yotzei *yotzei*? We've just talked that if it's already
פסול *pasul* that therefore you're not חייב chayav *chayav* anymore. So let's
take a look. So it says like this, what's his question? מהו
*mahu*? What's the story? כיון דיצא איפסל ליה ביוצא *Keivan d'yatza ipsal
leh b'yotzei*, since you took it out, it became פסול *pasul* with
יוצא yotzei *yotzei*. וכי הדר מחמיץ machmitz ליה *V'ki hadar machmitz leh*,
and now you're מחמיץ machmitz *machmitz* it, you're doing one of the
next stages with it being חמץ chametz *chametz*, לא מחייב mechayiv עלה
*lo mechayev aleh*, you're not חייב chayav *chayav* because it's already פסול
*pasul*. We said you're not חייב chayav *chayav* on something that's פסול
*pasul*. לא מחייב ליה משום מחמיץ machmitz אחר מחמיץ machmitz *lo mechayev
leh mishum machmitz achar machmitz*. You're not חייב chayav *chayav* for making
it חמץ chametz *chametz* the next stage. משום מחמיץ machmitz אחר מחמיץ
*mishum machmitz achar machmitz*. You made it חמץ chametz *chametz* in an
earlier stage but continuing to do the next stages while it's חמץ
chametz *chametz*, that you're not חייב chayav *chayav* for. או דילמא *o
dilma*, or do we say, כיון דחמצה פסול *keivan d'chamtza pasul*, since
you already made it חמץ chametz, *chametz*, פסול יוצא לא מהני בה
*psul yotzei lo mahni beh*. So the when you made it פסול
*pasul* you didn't make it any more פסול *pasul*. When I was
kneading it and I let it become חמץ chametz *chametz*, it was
already פסול *pasul*. Now I took it out of the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash*, I haven't made it more פסול *pasul*, right? It was
already פסול *pasul* because I let it become חמץ chametz. *chametz*. So
since it was already פסול *pasul*, so once that's true, וכי הדר
מחמיץ ליה *v'ki hadar machmitz leh*, now I bring it back into
the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash* and I continue to do something with it
חמץ chametz *chametz*, I bake it. So in that case, מחייב עלה
משום מחמיץ אחר מחמיץ *mechayev aleh mishum machmitz achar machmitz*. I would
be חייב chayav *chayav* for doing a next stage of the process.
You can't say that the fact that it became פסול *pasul* took
this somehow off the track of being חייב chayav *chayav* because it
was already פסול *pasul*. Okay, so here's what we're saying.
Since anytime I do multiple stages with it חמץ chametz *chametz* in
a later stage, it's already פסול *pasul* and I'm still חייב chayav
*chayav*, right? That's the חידוש *chiddush* of מחמיץ אחר מחמיץ *machmitz achar
machmitz*, right? That I'm חייב chayav *chayav* on the later stages because
I was even though it was already פסול *pasul* at an earlier
stage because of חמץ chametz *chametz*. So maybe therefore if it started
as חמץ chametz *chametz* and started פסול *pasul* and you introduced a
new פסול *psul* that does not get it off the track of
being able to be חייב chayav *chayav* for. This stays on the
track that now it can be חייב chayav *chayav* for doing this
as חמץ chametz, *chametz*, and the point was even if it remains
פסול *pasul* even if even though it was פסול *pasul* because חמץ
chametz, *chametz*, so the introduction of a new פסול *psul* is not
a sufficient to get it off the track.
פסול *pasul* doesn't make it back to כשר *kasher*.
You never would be כשר *kasher* again,
you don't want it to be. Oh right. But the fact that
we call it פסול *pasul* doesn't bring it back,
ah right, but מחמיץ *machmitz*... פסול *pasul* is never כשר *kasher*, פסול
*pasul* is exactly. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not have an
answer to that. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תיקו teiku. *teiku*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says we don't know the answer, that's a
really good question, we don't know the answer. וכי הדר מחמיץ ליה
מחייב עלה משום מחמיץ אחר מחמיץ תיקו *v'ki hadar machmitz leh mechayev
aleh mishum machmitz achar machmitz teiku*. We don't know the answer. Personally,
you know, to me it seems that it's obvious that you should
be פטור *patur* here, but nobody asked me. Because to me that
it's not like... I know Michael would normally say, I think... Whatever.
So here I really do think, I think that this case you
should be פטור for, because when the תורה Torah says okay, you're
חייב chayav if you do multiple stages of חמץ, chametz so fine.
We're almost looking at it as a continuation of a process and
it's still one new problem you've introduced חמץ chametz into this bread.
So although it came in multiple stages and multiple pieces whatever, we're
still saying it's all part of the same package of having brought
חמץ chametz. into this bread, we can bracket the fact that it
was already פסול because of חמץ. chametz But if it's פסול for
some other reason, then don't look at me that I now did
something wrong that I brought חמץ chametz into this bread, this thing
was already off the track regardless. Anyway, that רב פפא'ס קנס is
obvious, and he brings that once it started as being פסול because
of חמץ chametz, and we ignored it, we're going to ignore and
bracket other פסולים psulim as well and we're going to be prepared
to be מחייב you. Okay, let's take a look at a related
question. בעי רב
מרי, Bai Rav Mari, so רב מרי Rav Mari asked of a
question. חימצה בראשו של מזבח מהו. Chimsa b'rosh ishomizbe'ach mahu. Let's say
I took this קומץ kometz and I well let's just give you
an obvious case so he's not asking and then you'll appreciate his
case. I took the קומץ kometz and I put it on the
מזבח mizbe'ach. and I allowed it to burn, and let's say here
it is it's burning let's say even the majority of it is
burned so like I've offered up the קומץ, kometz, but let's say
it was placed on the fire in such a way that the
majority of it burned and some part of it is has remained
raw. Okay. And now I go ahead and I am מחמיץ that
amount. Now what does it mean I'm מחמיץ it? What am I
exactly doing? I don't know but I throw a little sourdough into
it after although half of it is already gone. So there we're
going to say there you're definitely פטור because the תורה Torah says,
כל המנחה אשר תקריבו אתם, kol hamincha asher takrivu atem, which you
will offer to God, not something that you've already offered it to
God. Once it's already been offered, you're not חייב. chayav Okay, it's
a process issue. Okay, right. So, now his question is, let's say
though it hasn't started burning. Let's say it's just up at the
top of the מזבח. mizbe'ach, Is that אשר asher is that are
you still saying that you have yet to offer to God or
the fact that you brought it to the top of the מזבח
mizbeiach. it's already been brought to God although it has not burned
yet?
If I just decided like you know אימורים, emurim, all right, up
on the מזבח and put them on the fire.
Right. So let's take a look at what it says. So it
says like this. Okay. חימצה בראשו של מזבח מהו. Chimsa b'rosh ishomizbe'ach
mahu.
What's the status? אשר תקריבו Asher takrivu אמר רחמנא amar rachmana that
you will offer ואקרבו v'akravo
you brought it close meaning we're reading תקריבו, takrivu, and of course
Michael is completely correct, nobody is saying that I'm יוצא the מנחה,
mincha, you know the מנחה mincha you're יוצא when you put the
קומץ kometz on the fire. Nobody's saying I'm יוצא if here I
am holding it at the top of the מזבח. But what it's
suggesting is how you read the word תקריבו. takrivu.
Is it לאקריבו l'akrivo as
like to bring close essentially? And therefore you've essentially already brought it
close? Or are you reading תקריבו takrivu to literally mean offer up
and it has yet to full been offered? Okay, ואקרבו לה v'akravo
la and you've already brought it close. או דילמא מחוסר הקטרה כמחוסר
מעשה דמי? O dilma mechusar haktara k'mechusar ma'aseh dami? It has yet
to be burned, and therefore since it has yet to be burned,
it's not considered like it's already been offered. Which also reflects on
the earlier סיפא. seifa. It wasn't just that the word הקריב hakriv
means to bring close, but since it's about to be burned, it's
like it's burned and you're no longer able to be חייב chayav
for it. What does Michael say is strange? Why should we say
that? Anyway the גמרא Gemara ends with a תיקו. We're not exactly
sure what stage you are the חיוב chiyuv stops. So what have
we said? It applies to all מנחות, minchos, all parts of the
מנחה, mincha, the מנחה mincha as a whole, the קומץ, kometz, the
שיריים. shirayim. What was also said is because of the phrase of
אשר תקריבו, asher takrivu, you're only חייב chayav if it could be
going on the מזבח, not if it's פסול. And now we're saying
you're only חייב until it has yet to be offered and we're
trying to figure out what is that moment where it's considered to
be offered or for as if it were offered. And now the
גמרא Gemara asks on that in a related way.
But I don't know what happens if I actually ate the שיריים.
shirayim.
Right. Okay.
והשתא דנפקא ליה מכל המנחה אשר תקריבו, V'hashta d'nafkilei mi'kol hamincha asher
takrivu, since we learned out from
the oh take out that s. Since we learned out from כל
המנחה, kol hamincha, since we learned out from the word כל המנחה
kol hamincha it applies to every מנחה, mincha אשר תקריבו asher takrivu
למה לי? lama li? What am I learning with the phrase אשר
תקריבו? asher takrivu? Now that's a very bizarre question as תוספות Tosfos
points out. We just said what you're learning from this phrase אשר
תקריבו. asher takrivu. First of all, that if it's פסול and it's
not fit to be brought up you're exempt. And number two, that
after a certain stage of after having been brought up you can't
be חייב either. It's only until it's being brought, not once it's
brought. For whatever reason the גמרא Gemara is bracketing what we just
said before of what we learned from אשר תקריבו asher takrivu and
is going to now learn something else from אשר תקריבו. asher takrivu.
So let's take a look. It says, מיבעי ליה לכדתניא. mibayei lei
l'khidetanya. What we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, אשר תקריבו, asher takrivu,
what did we act what does it say אשר תקריבו? asher takrivu?
That you're חייב when the מנחה mincha that you will bring, until
to include even more מנחות. minchos. Anything you'll bring. Not only your
standard מנחה mincha but any type of מנחה mincha you'll bring. What's
any, what would I have thought not? So לרבות מנחת נסכים לחימוץ.
l'rabos minchas nesachim l'chimutz. To tell you you're חייב even on a
מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, the מנחה mincha. of flour and oil that
comes with a קרבן. korban.
דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי.
Divrei Rabbi Yose HaGelili. That's what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili
says. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, לרבות לחם הפנים לחימוץ. l'rabos
lechem hapanim l'chimutz. To include לחם הפנים lechem hapanim to חימוץ. chimutz.
include לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Now why are these saying things that
I would have thought are not included? So think about in a
minute what some special problems with them are. מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim
maybe didn't have water and therefore maybe couldn't become חמץ. לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim we'll see,
might not have- the way you would have made it, might have
been in כלים keilim where it was not yet קודש kodesh or
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf until it was actually baked or put on
the שולחן. shulchan. And therefore, if it doesn't yet have קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf until it's baked, there's no way you'd be חייב for
making it חמץ or it happens before it's baked. So these are
things which we'll see in a minute there would have been reason
to exclude. So אשר תקריבו asher takrivu is telling me you're חייב
even on these for making them חמץ. Although it's a debate of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGalili and
it presumably they disagree with one another. One says you're חייב on
לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, you're חייב on מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim not.
And this says no, you're חייב on לחם הפנים lechem hapanim but
you're not חייב on מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, exactly for the problems
that we're about to raise, that these things are more questionable, are
they fit for becoming חמץ. תוספות Tosafos also points out that it's
not just- are they more questionable? Because let's say, for example, the
way we answer the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim as we'll see is
it can become חמץ because you're allowed to use water with it
or you do use water. So then it gets back to the
question- so then why did I need a פסוק pasuk to include
it? If it doesn't have that problem, if actually you do use
water for it and it can become חמץ, why did I need
a special פסוק? pasuk? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both point
out there are other reasons why these are not standard מנחות. menachos.
And it's basically two things. Number one is the, certainly by the
what do you call it? By the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim it's
fully burned. A standard מנחה mincha. is eaten. Now that's not a
good example by the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. לחם הפנים lechem hapanim
is eaten. But there's other ways in which it's different. לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim does not have a part of it itself being put
on המזבח. hamizbeiach. It has something else, the
קטורת ketores being put on- sorry, the לבונה levonah being put on.
So you either don't have- so either you don't have it being
eaten or you don't have part of it being put on המזבח.
hamizbeiach. Now again, there are other cases like that. מנחת כהנים minchas
kohanim isn't eaten. But you have other ways in which it's different.
The מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim has oil but it doesn't have לבונה.
levonah. The לחם הפנים lechem hapanim has לבונה, levonah, those are those
little things that you have on the table that you burn, but
it doesn't have oil. It's simply flour and water. So there are
ways in which these two even before you get to the questions
of חמץ are unusual types of מנחה. mincha And therefore you needed
a פסוק pasuk to include it. And what you have is רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGalili is including מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is including לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. And now
we're going to talk about why these might not- what the problems
might be about these becoming חמץ. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
When we had above when we said שאר מנחות מנין sha'ar menachos
minayin תלמוד לומר כל המנחה. talmud lomar kol hamincha.
So that's like a third opinion that would have said of even
everything, for every single one of them no matter what.
No, שאר מנחות sha'ar menachos is other standard מנחות menachos because the
פסוק pasuk was written by מרחשת. marcheses. And now what we're saying
is the reason you need אשר תקריבו asher takrivu is we're even
including non-standard מנחות. menachos.
So that- so there- so they're really talking about two separate things.
First we have to establish all of the standard מנחות menachos that
are written in ויקרא צו- Vayikra Tzav מרחשת, marcheses, מחבת, machavas, בלולה
בשמן, belulah bashemen, חרבה, charevah,
right?
So we have all standard. And now we're saying שאר מנחות sha'ar
menachos means all standard. All standard מנחות menachos says it blanket. Right?
So that's why רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos say that even though
we said שאר מנחות, sha'ar menachos, because לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and
מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim are non-standard, we would not have known they
were included. Okay now we're going to ask why is it that
they deserve to be included? Let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this. מנחת נסכים מי פירות הם. minchas nesachim mei peiros
heim. One minute. The מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim it's- where's the water?
It's only oil and flour. ומי פירות אינם מחמיצים. umei peiros einam
machmitzim. It can't become חמץ. מי פירות?
mei peiros? So oil.
Oil is right, oil is a derivative of a- it's not water.
Anything that's not water
is
מי פירות. mei peiros. And anyway oil is מי פירות mei peiros
because it comes from olives. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ריש
לקיש amar Reish Lakish אמר האי רבי יוסי הגלילי amar hai Rabbi
Yose HaGalili you're right, but רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGalili who
said that you're prohibited for חמץ, he used to say מנחת נסכים
מגדבלה במים וכשרה minchas nesachim migadbelah bemayim ukesheirah that you can add
water to your מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim and it's כשרה. kesheirah. Doesn't
sound like you have to add water, because he says the word
וכשרה, ukesheirah, which means it'll be okay, it'll still be כשרה. kesheirah.
So you're allowed to add water to your מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim
and therefore the תורה Torah has to tell you if you added
water to your מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, don't let it become חמץ
and then you'll transgress this. If by adding water you invalidated it,
we've already learned you're not חייב for letting something פסול become חמץ.
But if you added water and now we're saying that that will
remain כשרה, kesheirah, then it's saying if you happen to have done
that, don't let it become חמץ. Has a question, רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafos both ask this, all of a sudden the גמרא Gemara
woke up to the fact that the תורה Torah never mentions water
by the מנחות? menachos? All the מנחות menachos it says oil, it
doesn't say water. So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both give the
same answer. They say no, that we always assumed you needed water
by the others although the תורה Torah doesn't say it, because you
can't make the mixture without the water. Why? Because there's not a
lot of oil. And since there's not a lot of oil by
the other ones, we assumed you would have needed extra water to
make it. But here by מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, if you remember,
the proportions are very different, there's three times as much oil as
there is in a normal מנחה. mincha, So here we assumed you
were not going to add any liquid, you were just going to
do it with the oil since the תורה Torah doesn't say water.
And now what we're saying- and therefore we said it can't become
חמץ and that's why רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGalili has to
say no. baked. Not by the others, which is quite fascinating, I
mean you
get to the
whole תורה'ס Torah's prohibition of לא תעשה חמץ lo saaseh chametz is
by מרחשת, meracheshes, which is not baked, right? And why does the
גמרא Gemara, single this problem out? I don't know. Unless the רמב"ם
Rambam would say, I don't know, that the גמרא Gemara also maybe
all maybe you only need water by the others, but it took
it for granted that you could add water, you know, in the
non-baked things, not that you needed to, but that you could. But
we didn't but and now what we're saying is that even by
the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim you can add water. The upshot though
it is that because we have a problem of חמץ by all
of these things, you have to assume that there's water as part
of it, even though the תורה Torah. never mentions water. And therefore
you have to assume that water is one of the ingredients going
on.
So that's how it could be one of the ingredients that way
you could potentially do it, but even usually because you don't.
Exactly. The other way to say it is not that water has
to be an ingredient, but it could be an ingredient and you
need the prohibition, which is what the גמרא Gemara is saying by
מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim and what I think the רמב"ם Rambam would
say by all the מנחות menachos that are non-baked מנחות. menachos. Okay,
but at least water could be an ingredient, although again, it's not
mentioned anywhere in the תורה. Torah Now that's why we're how we
can include מנחת נסכים. minchas nesachim. Now let's look about including the
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
לחם הפנים מידת יבש, lechem hapanim midas yavesh, one minute, לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim is dry measure. What does that mean? Well, let's first
read finish the sentence, ושמעינה ליה לרבי עקיבא דאמר מידת יבש לא
נתקדשה. u’shaminah lei l’Rebbi Akiva d’amar midas yavesh lo niskadshah. And רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva we know in another סוגיא, sugya, right, for anybody
that's learned I think בכורות Bechoros or whatever, that רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva says or later anyway later in this גמרא, Gemara I'm sorry,
later in this גמרא Gemara in דף צ"ד, daf tzadi daled, רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says the dry measuring vessels were not נתקדש קדושת
הגוף. niskaadesh kedushas haguf. What does that mean? It means, so you
had in the בית המקדש, you had כלי שרת, klei shares, things
which were definitely used, which were anointed and sanctified and could give
קדושה kedusha to items that were put in them. For example, the
thing you used to catch the blood when you שחט shacht a
קרבן, korban, that thing is a כלי שרת, kli shares, you know,
the blood is going in, it's being sanctified, it's being put on
the מזבח. But then you also had your measuring cups. Okay, I
got my עשרון isaron measuring cup and I got my this measuring
cup and it's whatever. So
here's the word מידה. midah. מידה midah means a measuring vessel, a
מידה, midah, measure, a measuring vessel. So were the measuring vessels sanctified?
So רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says the dry measuring vessels which you'll
use for measuring your flour was not sanctified. We'll see in a
minute, learned from פסוקים, pesukim, whatever reason, he assumes they were not.
I don't know why, but they weren't. So therefore we're going to
say how are you going to get לחם הפנים lechem hapanim to
become to transgress? Why? It's sort of like the question people were
raising before. What if you haven't made it a מנחה mincha, yet?
So that's what so here we're assuming you only transgress חמץ not
only if I sanctified this flour for the sake of a מנחה,
mincha but it gets קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. It gets what's considered
intrinsic קדושה, kedusha, and that comes by animals it comes earlier, but
by מנחות menachos we assume that that comes only when it comes
in contact with a כלי שרת. kli shares. So when does so
you can only start transgressing חמץ after it's been in contact with
a כלי שרת. kli shares. So if I say that the dry
measures were so what if I what do I do by the
לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim? I measure out my flour, what else goes
into the ingredients for לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim? Water, water, there's no
specific measure for water, so I just put in whatever however much
water I need. I knead it, whatever, still it's not come in
contact with wait, you
need to turn on on a so you're
saying where are you doing the kneading? We'll get to that in
a minute, we'll bracket that, that you're kneading on a flat surface.
Okay, I
don't need to put it on a I don't know, afterwards.
Afterwards, getting to. I go and I knead it, I bake it,
when does it first come in contact with a כלי שרת? kli
shares? Either the oven is a כלי שרת, kli shares, but okay
we'll get there. Either the oven is a כלי שרת kli shares
or the שלחן shulchan is a כלי שרת, kli shares, certainly. But
if it only becomes in contact with a כלי שרת kli shares
after it's baked or then I can't become חייב for מחמיץ because
the מחמיץ happened beforehand. So that's why רבי that's why the גמרא
Gemara is saying is how do you have חמץ, the prohibition on
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim if it did not become sanctified with the
dry measure? Now one minute, the question is what about every single
מנחה, mincha? right? Why don't we say the same problem? If the
measure wasn't קדוש, kadosh, how did it become yet קדוש kadosh in
order for you to transgress? No, because every other מנחה mincha, has
not only the ingredients of flour, but what else is on the
ingredient list of every other מנחה? mincha. Oil. Oil
and a certain measure of oil, not however much you want. So
and that's well yes, but it's also a liquid, so when I
am making every other מנחה, mincha, I have to measure out my
oil. There I'm not using a מידת יבש, midas yavesh, I'm using
a מידת לח. midas lach. I'm using a measuring cup for liquid
which we are going to see everybody agrees was נתקדש. niskaadesh. Again,
I don't know why to make the difference. So therefore no problem
about being חייב in חמץ for everything else because I measure out
my oil, the oil has become קדוש קדושת הגוף, kadosh kedushas haguf,
the whole now מנחה'ס mincha's קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf and I transgress
if I let it become חמץ. But when I'm making לחם הפנים,
lechem hapanim, nothing has been the flour wasn't in contact with a
כלי שרת. kli shares. I didn't use my measuring vessels.
I used measuring vessels but they were dry. The water isn't קדוש
kadosh כלי שרת kli shares because I didn't use my measuring vessels.
So what do you use? I just took a cup.
I didn't need a measuring vessel. You don't need a measuring vessel
for the water and therefore it's not yet קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf.
How could I be חייב for חמץ if it doesn't have קדושת
הגוף? kedushat haguf? That's the גמרא's Gemara question. Okay, I also had
to add
I don't know what this is called, but you know you have
to use like a flat surface to get it from whatever you
need to do to into the oven, and that wasn't a כלי
שרת? kli shares?
Not so sure, so maybe it doesn't have to be. But we'll
see in a minute. The גמרא's Gemara more or less going to
ask that question. Okay, the גמרא's Gemara going to say you had
to knead it somewhere, wouldn't that? So we'll see what the גמרא
Gemara asks. Okay, but at least now that's how it's framing the
question. Okay.
But it could
only become חמץ in the oven though, right?
Yes, it could be. The question is was the oven the כלי
שרת kli shares or not? Was the very putting it in, you
know if the only כלי שרת kli shares was the שולחן, shulchan,
then it's already been totally baked before it even comes in contact
with the כלי שרת, kli shares, right? And that's right.
Although I mean they've baked, you know they slapped it in the
oven we had that whole whatever it's called.
Right. Okay. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
since רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds מדת יבש לא נתקדשה, midat yavash
lo nitkadsha, how can you be חייב for חמץ on the לחם
הפנים lechem hapanim if it doesn't have קדושה kedusha until after it's
baked? So the גמרא Gemara says, שלח shlach whoever it is, whether
ראובן Reuven or רבין, Ravin, משמיה דרבי יוחנן, mishmei de'Rabbi Yochanan, so
they sent a message from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that's what שלח
shlach means. ככי אפתר שיב משנא, kachi ippatar sheiv mishna, here's the
way to lay out the משנה, mishna, ואיפוך, ve'ippuch, meaning our explanation
was correct that it is this issue about you know debating whether
it's לחם הפנים lechem hapanim or the מנחת נסכים. minchas nesachim. The
only problem is you have to reverse the names. You got the
names reversed. Okay, what's the reverse? אשר תקריב לראבות לחם הפנים לקיים
דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי. asher takriv lera'avos lechem hapanim lekayem divrei Rabbi
Yossi HaGlili. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili is the one who
is saying that it is the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim that you're
חייב for, that that can, you've transgressed. רבי עקיבא אומר לראבות מנחת
נסכים לחימוץ, Rabbi Akiva omer lera'avos minchas nesachim lechimmutz, that it's only
to be חייב on מנחת נסכים. minchas nesachim. So it is the
same debate but you got to reverse the names because of the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva problem. So now we are saying the one
that says you're חייב for לחם הפנים lechem hapanim held that what?
מדת יבש נתקדשה, midas yavash nitkadsha, that the dry measures did have
קדושה kedusha and therefore the flour did have קדושה kedusha and therefore
it was possible to transgress חמץ on the flour while you were
before it was baked. Okay, so is that clear? The problem with
לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, can you transgress? Of course you can allow
the bread to become חמץ, right? The problem is have you transgressed
if the bread has not yet been sanctified? Because otherwise just throw
it out and start again. What's to define that I made the
מנחה חמץ? mincha chametz? To make the מנחה חמץ mincha chametz the
bread has to be sanctified. And therefore we have to say the
one that says you transgressed with לחם הפנים lechem hapanim has to
say that the dry measures were נתקדשה. nitkadsha. Yes.
Is this possible for us to think of this מחלוקת machlokes conceptually
as a distinction between whether or not קדושה kedusha is because of
intentionality or because of the similar to the way that טומאה tumah
requires liquid in order to...
Right, so I don't want to go there right now. I don't
want to go there right now because right now the גמרא Gemara
is not saying that there's any debate of how. There is a
question by the way of אין כלי שרת מקדשין אלא לדעת, ein
klei shares mikadshin ela lada'as, which gets into your point about intentionality.
But here we're not talking about how קדושה kedusha works, just a
very practical question. Were they, did they sanctify the מדת יבש? midas
yavash?
I was trying to understand the difference between solid or between dry
and wet could be as simple as if the כלי kli imparts
it the way טומאה tumah is imparted.
Right, the כלי kli certainly has more, does more for wet for
something wet than it does to something dry, because it holds it
more. That's true. But here it's a practical question of whether they
sanctify the כלי, kli, not whether the כלי kli operates on the
thing. Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. ואזל רבי יוחנן לטעמיה, ve'azal Rabbi Yochanan leta'ameih, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan goes according to his reason, because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
now basically has רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili saying dry measures
were נתקדש. nitkadesh. He goes according to his reason, דאמר רבי יוחנן
רבי יוסי הגלילי ואחד מתלמידי רבי ישמעאל אמרו דבר אחד. de'amar Rabbi
Yochanan Rabbi Yossi HaGlili ve'achad mitalmidei Rabbi Yishmael amru davar echad. רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili and one of the students of רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said basically the same point. ומנו, umano, who is
this student of רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? רבי יאשיה. Rabbi Yoshiya. דתניא,
detanya, we taught in the ברייתא. braisa. וימשחם ויקדש אותם. vayimshachem vayikadesh
osam. This is by משה Moshe sanctifying the כלי שרת, klei shares,
okay, and he sanctified them and we're assuming that the basic כלי
שרת klei shares the Torah is talking about for מרדכי's Mordechai reason
basically what you need vessels for are for liquids. So base assumption
here is liquid vessels. And it says he sanctified them and there's
an extra word ויקדש אותם, vayikadesh osam, which is normally a limiting
word. So how's it limiting? רבי יאשיה אומר מדת הלח נמשחו בין
מבפנים בין מבחוץ, Rabbi Yoshiya omer midas halach nimshachu bein mibifnim bein
mibachutz, liquid measures were anointed on the inside and the
outside. ומדת יבש נמשחו מבפנים ואין נמשחו מבחוץ, umidat yavash nimshachu mibifnim
ve'ein nimshachu mibachutz, only anointed on the inside not on the outside.
So it wasn't exactly the same, but even though that's true, they
were still sanctified. And therefore even the dry measures were sanctified. Why
outside versus inside? I don't know. Just אותם osam is limiting. And
since he knows outside not inside? Because basically since it transfers its
קדושה kedusha by coming in contact with the stuff put in it,
we want to make sure minimally that it is נמשח nimshach on
the inside. Okay, why not on the outside, that I don't know.
Okay, but the basic point is he admits that there's some ways
it's different but he doesn't want to give up on the מדת
יבש midas yavash being having the ability to be מקדש what you
put in on them. That's what רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says.
And now we have רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonatan omer, רבי יונתן
Rabbi Yonatan says no. מדת הלח נמשחו מבפנים. midat halach nimshachu mibifnim.
Once they're lower, liquid measures are on the inside not on the
outside, so but they are מקדש what's put into them. מידת יבש
לא נמשכו כל עיקר. Midas yavesh lo nimshechu kol ikar. Dry measures
were not sanctified at all. תא דאחוי לך Ta dachvei lach and
I'll prove to you that we can never, that there's a reason.
Michael's asking what's the reason? Maybe I'll prove to you and maybe
it's also the reason how you know that dry measures were not
sanctified. שהרי אין מקודשות, Sheharei ein mekudashot, דכתיב dechtiv that they're not
sanctified because it says ממושבותיכם תביאו לחם תנופה שתים שני עשרונים סלת
תהיינה חמץ תאפינה בכורים להשם. Mimoshvoseichem tavyiu lechem tenufa shtayim shnei esronim
solet tihyena chametz teiafena bikurim l'Hashem.
The פסוק pasuk about bringing the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem on שבועות,
Shavuot, right? So it says you shall bring from your places this,
you know, these two loaves of bread, you know, two עשרונים, esronim,
you shall, you shall bake them into חמץ, בכורים להשם. bikurim l'Hashem.
Now what's the problem? What does that prove? Because he says אימתי
הם להשם לאחר שנאפו. Eimasi heim l'Hashem l'achar shenaafu.
He's reading the פסוק pasuk like this: חמץ תאפינה, chametz teiafena,
after you've baked them, then בכורים להשם. bikurim l'Hashem. Then we can
call them בכורים. bikurim. We can't call them בכורים bikurim earlier. You
know why? Because they didn't have any sanctity earlier, they didn't have
intrinsic sanctity. So therefore they can only be called בכורים bikurim after
they've been baked because the oven has קדושה. kedusha. The oven will
sanctify them. Prior to that they will not be sanctified. So that's
how he says that proves me that the dry measures and the
שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem like the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim only had
water, did not have oil, so never you never needed to use
the liquid measures for the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem and therefore the
קדושה kedusha by these things happens only after they are baked. Okay,
so now you see that רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan goes according to
his reasoning because here רבי יאשיה Rebi Yoshiya says that the שתי
הלחם Shtei Halechem that the dry measures did have קדושה kedusha and
therefore you could have a חמץ problem with the לחם הפנים Lechem
Hapanim and says that he says the same thing as רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rebi Yosi Haglili and this is רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan saying
that it was רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebi Yosi Haglili who says you
transgress חמץ for the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim because the dry measures
did have קדושה kedusha and therefore you could transgress חמץ. Yes.
Now this is separate from מעילה, me'ila, right? Because if there's no
קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf it will still be מועל moel in it
if I decide to use it.
No, if it's קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. But to be חייב for
חמץ it's not enough for the, the question you could ask which
Tosafos up there is I don't know who needs a כלי? kli?
I'll just say I'm מקדיש makdish this flour to be used for
a מנחה. But the point is that until then it's still קדושת
דמים. kedushat damim. It's owned by the הקדש. Heikdesh. The assumption here
is to be חייב for מחמיץ you need it to be קדושת
הגוף, kedushat haguf, intrinsically defined as a מנחה, and that will only
happen we are assuming and this is the way מנחות minchot are
different than animals when it comes in contact with a כלי שרת.
kli sharet. Okay let's just read a little bit more.
Okay. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? What do they debate? באותם. B'osam. The
word אותם. osam. רבי יוסי סבר אותם למעוטי מידת יבש מבחוץ. Rebi
Yosi savar osam l'mueiti midas yavesh mibachutz. So that's just,
really isn't explicating it much, I mean really isn't explaining as much
as just spelling it out. רבי יאשיה Rebi Yoshiya says אותם osam
excludes the dry measures, but only excludes them partially. They're not sanctified
on the outside. They're still sanctified on the inside. רבי יונתן סבר
Rebi Yonatan savar and רבי יונתן Rebi Yonatan held the opinion מידת
יבש חול הוא. Midas yavesh chol hu. He starts with the assumption
that the dry measures were never קדוש. kadosh. If that's the assumption
you're starting with which you learned out from לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
it only becomes קדוש kadosh after it's baked, same as שתי הלחם,
Shtei Halechem, so obviously it's not קדוש. kadosh. So therefore how, what's
אותם osam needed for then? So therefore ולא יצטריך קרא למעוטי. v'lo
itztarich kra l'mueiti. You don't need a פסוק pasuk to tell you
don't sanctify dry measures. He starts by assuming they're not קדוש. kadosh.
האי דצריך קרא למעוטי Hai deztarich kra l'mueiti what is the פסוק
pasuk limiting? מידת לח מבחוץ. Midas lach mibachutz. Don't even fully sanctify
the liquid measures, only do the inside don't do the outside. Fine.
But that's the debate. One starts with the assumption based on the
פסוק pasuk about שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem dry measures are not מתקדש.
miskadesh. The other starts with the assumption that it is and therefore
if it's limited it's only partially limited inside not outside. Now let's
just read one a little bit. לימא נמי רבי עקיבא ואחד מתלמידי
רבי ישמעאל אמרו דבר אחד ומנו רבי יונתן? Leima nami Rebi Akiva
v'chad mitalmidei Rebi Yishmael amru davar echad u'manu Rebi Yonatan? Why did
you only line up רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebi Yosi Haglili and רבי
יאשיה? Rebi Yoshiya? Why not line up the other two opinions? רבי
עקיבא Rebi Akiva says you don't transgress for לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
which presumably means he holds, why don't you transgress? Because the dry
measures were not נתקדש. nitkadesh. And say he says the same thing
as רבי יונתן Rebi Yonatan who says the dry measures were not
נתקדש. nitkadesh. Why'd you only line up the two of the opinions?
The other two line up as well. Okay, so הגמרא hag'mara says,
no. משום דלא שוו במידת הלח להדדי. Mishum d'lo shavu b'midas halach
l'hadadi.
Because they don't agree with the issue of מידת לח. midas lach.
What does this mean? It means that we know elsewhere that רבי
עקיבא'ס Rebi Akiva's position is, that רבי יונתן, Rebi Yonatan, one minute,
ah, that רבי עקיבא'ס Rebi Akiva's position is that מידת לח midas
lach that was sanctified not only on the inside but inside and
outside. So although there's no functional difference for us whether it's inside
or inside and outside either way the liquid measures sanctify what's put
in them you can't say they hold the exact same opinion. רבי
עקיבא Rebi Akiva holds it's inside and outside and רבי יונתן Rebi
Yonatan holds it's only inside. But effectively these positions line up. רבי
עקיבא Rebi Akiva says you do not you do not
transgress for לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. Why not? Because it only uses
dry measures and dry measures were not נתקדש nitkadesh so you can't
transgress. It doesn't yet have קדושה, kedusha, תפוס קדושה. tfos kedusha. And
רבי יאשיה Rebi Yoshiya says no the dry measures were נתקדש, nitkadesh,
it does have תפוס קדושה tfos kedusha and you can transgress, and
those line up with this debate about what. They did with the
כלי שרת. klei shares. Maybe we'll just read one more sentence here,
which is Michael's question about don't you use other ספלים? sefalim? So
just go, I know it's already 8:30, we'll just do one more
line, but אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. amar lei Rav Pappa le-Abaye.
Rav Pappa said to Abaye, והא איכא ביסה דלחמא? ve-ha ika bisa
de-lachma? One minute, there's the kneading trough. That's something, you know, that
takes dough in it, and it's for liquid, meaning it's for more,
not just simple dry stuff, but for more liquidy stuff. So why
how why are we assuming that it's all about the dry if
there's no dry measures if it's all about dry measures it's not
going to be קדוש? kadosh? Don't you use other vessels which were
sanctified? Okay, so now Michael's question about the tray to get it
to the oven is a מבעיא miba'aya because that's מדת יבש midat
yavesh presumably. That's something that serves, you know, non-dry things, but a,
right, a bowl, a kneading bowl is something that actually is is
serves to liquids as well and therefore is נתקדש. nitkadesh. Okay, so
shouldn't that introduce the problem earlier? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
ליה, amar lei, כגון דלשה על גבי קטבליא. kegon de-lasha al gabei
katbalya. So it says, okay, but you don't have to use the
bowl, the kneading bowl, you could do it on a on like
on a butcher block, you could do it on a flat surface.
So the תורה Torah can't tell you, don't make this חמץ if
the standard is you can't assume that it's going to be קדוש.
kadosh. Okay. So the גמרא says one minute, אי הכי, ei hachi,
דקאמר ליה רבי יונתן, de-ka'amar lei Rebbi Yonatan, תדע teidua דכלי שרת
אין מקדשין אלא בפנים. de-klei shares ein mikadshin ela bifnim. When Rebbi
Yonatan said that I'm going to prove to
you that the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem is not that the dry
measures are not קדוש kadosh because the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem only
becomes קדוש kadosh after it's baked, why didn't the גמרא say back
לימא ליה כגון דלשה בביסה דחול? leima lei kegon de-lasha be-bisa de-chol?
Why don't you say back, no, no, dry measures generally are קדוש.
kadosh. When does the תורה Torah say that the שתי הלחם shtei
ha-lechem only becomes קדוש kadosh when it's baked? If you happened to
use your your home measure, but it was חול. chol. But, but
if you actually use the one in the מקדש, then אין הכי
נמי, ein hachi nami, you would be right that it would
be it would it would be קדוש kadosh earlier. Meaning, the גמרא
saying, I know it's a little bit rushed to try to focus
on this, but the גמרא is saying is, how much are we
assuming the possibility of doing something in some way and how much
are we assuming whether it has to be? Once you're allowing the
idea, once you're saying you know why the תורה Torah can't prohibit
the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem for because it's possible to do it
without it becoming קדוש? kadosh? You could use a flat surface rather
than a mixing bowl. So it says what possibility? That's what we're
talking about? So if that's why it's not going to tell me
a prohibition of שתי הלחם, shtei ha-lechem, then how can you prove,
you know, the לחם הפנים, lechem ha-panim, how can you prove by
the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem case that dry measures are not קדוש?
kadosh? Maybe that case is dry measures are קדוש, kadosh, but that
case was you happened to use one from your home. So, you
know, if we're talking about possibilities. So let's just see the answer
and with this we'll end. So the גמרא says no,
היכי אשה? heichi asha? What type of comparison is that? בשלומא, bishlama,
when it comes to the kneading bowl, לא כתב רחמנא דליעבד בביסה,
lo katav rachmana de-leivad be-bisa, למימשפא. le-mimshapa. The תורה Torah never told
me I needed a kneading bowl. So therefore the תורה Torah isn't
going to assume that I'm using a kneading bowl. It's totally acceptable
to do it on a butcher block and to do it on
a table. There's no assumption that there exists a kneading bowl. So
כי לשה על גבי קטבליא לית לן בה. ki lasha al gabei
katbalya leit lan bah. If you did on a table, there's no
problem and the תורה Torah can't assume you're using a kneading bowl.
אלא עשרון, ela isaron, but when it comes to measuring, כיון דאמר
רחמנא עביד עשרון, keivan de-amar rachmana avid isaron, the תורה Torah is
telling you you have to have a measure of an עשרון, isaron,
you have to have a dry measure וחייל ביה, ve-chayal beih, and
measure with it. שביק עשרון דקודש וחייל בעשרון דחול? shavik isaron de-kodesh
ve-chayal be-isaron de-chol? When the תורה Torah is talking about how you
make it, it's not going to assume that you're not using the
standard measuring cup in the בית המקדש and you're using one from
your home. So basically yes, when it talks about the לחם הפנים
lechem ha-panim and שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem not becoming קדוש kadosh until
it's baked, we have to assume that you're making it the normal
way. What's the normal way? You use the measuring vessels that they
give you in the מקדש. And if that didn't make it קדוש,
kadosh, we can therefore learn from that that the dry measuring vessels
were not קדוש. kadosh. When it talks about making dough, we assume
the normal way. What's the normal way? Normal way doesn't have to
assume a kneading bowl, could be done on a table. And therefore,
if the תורה is telling you that there's a prohibition of making
חמץ, we're going to assume that that will not that does not
apply to bread because by bread by the שתי הלחם, shtei ha-lechem,
לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim we can't assume that you're using a kneading
bowl. So if you hold that only the liquid measures were קדוש,
kadosh, the prohibition doesn't apply to bread, not because bread couldn't become
קדוש, kadosh, it could the לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim if you used
a liquid measure, but it doesn't have to. And therefore the prohibition
never applied to it. Whereas if you hold that the dry measures
are קדוש, kadosh, then of course the prohibition would apply to the
לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim as well.
Okay, we'll.